Excuse me.
抱歉打扰
Constable Morse.
I loved your singing.
Morse警员 我喜欢你的歌
Dorothea Frazil. Oxford Mail.
We met briefly on the Tremlett case.
我是牛津日报的Dorothea Frazil
在Tremlett案子中我们见过
Oh, I remember you, of course.
噢是的 我记得你
"歌手探长" 这角度不错
It's a good angle:
"The Singing Detective".
It's better than the one
I've got presently.
比我现在要发的稿子好
I've no wish to see my name in
the papers, Miss Frazil.
我对上报纸不感兴趣 Frazil小姐
你看 光写本地艺术新闻
Covering for the local arts
correspondent
is never going to win me the
Pulitzer.
我是得不了普利策奖的
Just give me a quote. I'll see
there's something in it for you.
跟我说两句嘛 我来给你发掘亮点
要是真这么互惠互利
我们俩离贿赂和腐败也不远了
Any such recompense would
leave us both open to charges
of bribery and corruption.
不好意思失陪了
If you'll excuse me.
Good evening.
晚安
祝你报道写得顺利
Good luck with your story.
警员!
Constable!
I'll be off, then, Aunt.
阿姨 那我走啦
Phillip明天会回来看你的
Phillip will be in tomorrow
to see if there's anything you need.
他不是要排练吗 有时间来吗?
Will he have time? With the recital?
他确实工作紧张
He's working very hard.
但是来看你对他来说总是件好事
But coming to see you is
always good for him.
So...
How is he?
- 那...
- 他还好吗?
你能找块防水布把木头盖上吗?
我去撒尿休息下
Can you get a tarp over the timber?
I'm breaking my neck for a jimmy.
- 她怎么了?
- 跟你说了就是不大舒服罢了
What's the matter with her? I told
you. She's just not feeling right.
别走好吗?
Don't go. Please.
She's my mother, Lionel.
她是我妈妈啊 Lionel
I do love you, Evie.
我真的爱你 Evie
Fancy a pint?
If you're buying.
- 喝一杯不?
- 你掏钱就喝
不是 这是突发情况 刚发生的
No, it's an emergency job.
Just come in.
Some old girl's sprung a leak.
有个女的割伤了
I can't exactly leave her
in the lurch, can I?
我总不能撒手不管吧?
Yeah. Quick as I can, promise.
好的 我尽快回来 保证
Love you too.
我也爱你
Subtitles by MemoryOnSmells
http://UKsubtitles.ru.
Watch ya.
Morse.
- 小心
- Morse
This way, sir.
这边 长官
Yardman was doing his rounds about
five.
Yardman差不多5点的时候在巡查
看见货车门开着 觉得应该看一眼
Saw the wagon door open
and thought he'd take a look.
他多久查一次车?
How often does he check on the
rolling stock?
Start, middle and finish of
his turn most nights.
中午开始 到晚上一般都查完了
But this end, I think, not so much.
但是这边我估计不太查
These are all out of service.
Waiting on being broken up.
这些都是停用的车厢 等着报废呢
- This it?
- Sir.
- 就这?
- 是的 长官
- 你好 DeBryn医生
- 你好 督察
Doctor DeBryn.
Inspector.
No need to ask after cause,
I shouldn't have thought.
死亡原因很明显
Ligature strangulation. Almost
textbook.
典型的勒死
至于死亡时间..
As to the time...
Three pink elephants, two pink
elephants, one pink elephant.
3只粉红小象 2只粉红小象 1只粉红小象
- 昨晚9点到12点之间
Some time between nine and midnight.
She's an earring missing.
- 她丢了一只耳环
我派了一批学员过来帮忙做搜索了
I've a contingent of cadets
coming down to search.
Got a name for her?
Evelyn Balfour.
- 她叫什么名字?
- Evelyn Balfour
她在Cowley Bingo的酒吧做酒保
Um... She works behind the bar
at Cowley Bingo.
她先生见她最后一面是昨晚7点左右
Husband last saw her last night
about seven o'clock
when she left to visit
her sick mother.
她当时离家去看望生病的母亲
Wasn't he worried when she didn't
come back?
她没回家他也不担心?
她有可能留在娘家过夜
There was a possibility
she may stay overnight.
她和他先生说她母亲病了
She told her husband her mother was
ill.
Her mother's been spoken to.
Nothing wrong with her.
找人跟她母亲谈过了 完全没病
What's that in her mouth?
- 她嘴里的是什么?
A handkerchief.
- 手帕
Embroidered with the letter... D.
还绣了字母D
这地方幽会可不怎么浪漫啊
Hardly the most romantic spot
for a bit of how's-your-father.
- 够偏僻
- 就冲这个偏僻
Private.
It's got that going for it.
Beggars can't, I suppose.
要饭的就不行了
我们去找她先生 你在这边查查她的情况
We're going to take the husband.
You can do her work.
只要事实
Just the facts.
不要你的"理论"
Don't need confusing with any
"theories".
然后回局里继续值班 听到没?
Then you're back to the nick and
resume general duties. Right?
All was well with you and
Mrs Balfour?
你跟Balfour太太感情好吗?
No arguments?
No.
- 平时不吵架?
- 不吵
从来没有拌嘴? 你昨晚出门没有?
Never a cross word, eh?
Did you go out last night?
No. Just had my tea.
没有 在家喝茶呢
然后给孩子洗澡 哄他们上床
Got the children bathed
and put to bed.
我在算回扣呢
I was catching up on my returns.
你是个保险代理对吧?
You're an insurance agent.
That right?
Mutual and Provident.
What's that? Door-to-door?
Mutual和Provident 那是什么公司 上门推销的?
上门收款
Collecting payments.
Balfour太太晚上经常单独出门吗?
Mrs Balfour often go out alone of an
evening?
Only to see her mother.
她最近出门去看望她母亲
She's not been in the best of
health lately. Shingles.
她最近身体不太好 带状疱疹
Oh. How long's that been
going on then?
这样多久了?
Couple of months.
几个月了
Other than that, Mrs Balfour was
more of a home-bird, was she?
除此之外 Balfour太太多半待在家是吗?
是的
Oh, yes.
她在彩票点有时候会上晚班
不过是轮班的 除此之外呢...
She sometimes had a late turn at
the bingo, depending on the rota.
But otherwise...
Nice.
We just had it done.
- 真漂亮
Couple of months back.
- 我们几个月前才装修的
Evelyn一直想要这样的
Evelyn had been on for one.
她有个同事圣诞节的时候置办了一整套
A pal of hers at work had a matching
suite put in at Christmas.
You know what they're like.
你懂的
Balfour太太好像和别人在一起
Mrs Balfour looks to have been
carrying on with someone, sir.
Romantically?
外遇?
Morse说她同事都这么认为
Common knowledge at the
bingo hall where she worked,
according to Morse.
Morse? 他不是不办案了吗
Morse? I thought he'd been
returned to general duties.
是的长官
That's right, sir. He has.
He just happened to be in early
when the report came through.
案子来的时候他正好值早班
他是最早到现场去的人之一
Amongst the first on the scene.
她先生知道出轨的事吗?
Does the husband know about
the... infidelity?
看着不像
Not the impression he's giving.
Trying to protect her reputation
perhaps. Or his own.
- 可能想保护名声吧
- 保护自己的名声也有可能
没人想戴绿帽子
No man likes to be thought
a cuckold.
看起来也不像
Doesn't look as though he's
got it in him.
The fancy man, most likely.
估计是个帅哥吧
Just a matter of finding him then.
Hm?
那就只是找人的问题了?
偷车案的报告写好没?
You got that car theft written up
yet?
How's about you stick to
general duties
你好好值你的班
破案的事情你别插手行吗?
and let the rough boys deal
with the grown-up stuff?
他为什么要把车门开着?
Why did he leave the door open?
If it wasn't open
she could have lay in there for
days before being discovered.
要是门关着的话她就不容易被发现了
杀了人受到惊吓
Panicked, hasn't he,
once he's done her.
Fled the scene and forgot
to shut it after him.
匆忙逃离现场忘记关门
- 你不觉得这样卤莽了一点吗?
It's reckless. Don't you think?
- 他露了马脚
He made a mistake.
或是故意想让我们找到她
Or he wanted us to find her.
我没听到你在打字
I don't hear you typing.
偷车案
Car theft.
(再吻一次)
Oh!
Police! Open the door!
警察 开门
Hello! Police!
有人吗 警察
Did you close that door? Police.
Was that you?
是你关的门吗? 警察 是你吗?
No, sir.
不是我 长官
"Oon back-ee-o ankera".
Un Bacio Ancora (再吻一次)
"Oon back-ee-o ankera" ( 别炫耀)
Un bacio ancora.
All right.
这是什么意思?
So what's it mean?
"One kiss more." Italian.
"再吻一次" 意大利语
Un bacio ancora is Otello's last
line in Verdi's opera.
再吻一次是威尔第的歌剧奥赛罗的最后一句词
So what?
所以呢?
He sings it having strangled his
wife in a fit of jealousy.
他因嫉妒勒死了自己太太后唱了这首歌
他认为她把一块手帕给了另一名军官
He believes she's given a
handkerchief to another officer
以表爱慕
as a sign of her affections.
- 然后呢
- 他太太叫Desdemona
And?
His wife's name is Desdemona.
The handkerchief stuffed in
Evelyn Balfour's mouth
塞在Evelyn Balfour嘴里的手巾上
was embroidered with the initial D.
绣有字母D
你开玩笑吧 不是真的要考虑这个思路吧?
You're kidding? We're not really
giving this any weight, are we?
你不觉得挺有意思?
Interesting, don't you think?
也许 但也有可能几年前就写在门上了
Maybe. But that could've been
written up on the door years ago.
我们更像是要找一个叫Dave的
More likely we're looking
for a bloke called Dave,
than some bint called Desdemona.
而不是Desdemona
如果她约会的是个有格调的人
If this is some fancy man
she had on the go,
it'll have been a spur
of the moment thing.
这可能是即兴写的
正是
Exactly.
他怎么可能把这些东西写在门上
He's hardly going to hang about
writing all that on the door,
then sliding it out of view where
nobody could find it, is he?
然后藏在没有人能看见的角落呢?
It was found.
Sir?
- 不是被发现了吗
- 长官?
It's not as if anybody normal
would think to look there, is it?
正常人谁会看那里啊?
我是Thursday
Thursday.
Where's this?
在哪里?
Morse.
Morse
Deceased is one Grace Agnes Madison.
11th of the fourth, 1896.
死者叫Grace Agnes Madison 1896年4月11日出生
寡妇 她侄女Faye发现的尸体
Widowed. Found by her niece, Faye.
Just gone half-past ten this
morning.
早上10点半死的
Pathologist been notified?
He's on his way.
- 通知法医了吗
- 他在路上
但是听侄女说她身体不错
But she was in general good health
according to the niece.
Oh. She's outside if you
wanted a word.
噢 你要找她问话的话 她在外面
Madison太太是你婶婶吧?
Mrs Madison was your aunt, is that
right?
Married to my father's older
brother. Uncle Cedric.
是我父亲大哥Cedric伯伯的老婆
He's deceased, I understand.
他听说他也过世了
没错 62岁过世的
Yes. He died in '62.
Aunt Grace returned to England
the following year.
Grace婶婶第二年就回到英国了
- 从哪里回来的?
- 印度
From where?
India.
She was born in Witney, but she grew
up and lived most of her life there,
她在Witney出生的 但是几乎一辈子都待在印度
也是在那认识了Cedric叔叔
which is where she met Uncle Cedric.
- 最后一次见她是什么时候?
- 嗯 昨天...
When did you see her last?
Erm... Yesterday.
Aunt Grace was all the family
we had left.
Grace是我们唯一的亲人了
我们每天会过来看看她
One or other of us tried to
look in every day,
just to see if there was
anything she needed.
看看她是否有什么需要
One or the other of whom?
你们指的是谁?
我和我哥Phillip
Erm... My brother. Phillip.
Today was his turn -
今天该他来的
but he's presently rehearsing
for a piano recital.
但是他在为一个钢琴演奏会排练
上次见她的时候看着挺好的?
She seemed in good health
when you saw her last?
是的 如常在温室里忙活着
Yes. Pottering about the
conservatory as usual.
Grace婶婶是个小有名气的植物学家
Aunt Grace was a botanist
of some note.
她写了几本关于次大陆花卉的书
She'd written several books on the
flora of the subcontinent.
Doctor.
Morse.
- 你好 医生
- 你好 Morse
Anything?
有什么发现?
你是问有什么不正常的迹像吗?
By anything, I presume you mean,
anything suspicious?
No obvious signs of violence.
没有暴力迹象
All I can tell you for now is
that she died sometime
现在我能告诉你的只有她死于
昨天下午4点到7点之间
between four and seven o'clock
yesterday afternoon.
I'd be grateful if you get the
contents of the teapot taken away
for analysis.
你要是能把茶壶里的东西检验一下就最好不过了
The teapot? People do die of
natural causes, Morse.
茶壶? 不是所有人都是被谋杀的好吗 Morse
Think someone bumped her off
for the inheritance?
你觉得是有人为了遗产谋害她?
我觉得桌子摆了两人茶具
但是客人没有碰茶
I think the table's set for two, and
her guest hasn't touched their tea.
Hm. If that's the stuff the chimps
drink, I'm a Chinaman.
如果黑猩猩喝这个的话 那我就是中国佬了
Mrs Madison had an appointment
in her diary
Madison太太在日记里
with a Mister Nimmo at 4pm
yesterday.
记着昨天下午4点和Nimmo先生有约
There was a letter from him.
Dated Tuesday last.
还有一封他寄的信 日期是上周二
好像是个记者 想给她做园艺采访
Some sort of journalist.
Wanted to write about her gardening.
She was a botanist of some repute,
apparently.
貌似她是个有点声誉的植物学家
One day I'll send you out
for a routine enquiry
总有天我会给你个寻常案子
让你查不出特别的地方
and it'll turn out to be just that.
But I won't hold my breath.
虽然我觉得这不太可能
就是圣人的抽屉里你都能发现什么事不对劲
You'd find something suspicious
in a saint's sock drawer.
I didn't know you spoke Italian.
我不知道你懂意大利语呢
More under my hat than nits.
你不知道我的还多着呢
We came up through Italy after North
Africa. Landed at Reggio.
我们离开北非后去了意大利 在Reggio登陆
Then on to Cassino.
然后去了Cassino
Got a match on a thumbprint
off Mrs Balfour's handbag, sir.
Balfour太太手提包上有个指纹查出来了
Roy Adamson.
是Roy Adamson的
九年前因收赃判了缓刑三个月
Three months suspended for
receiving, some nine years back.
Runs a builder's yard out
towards Headington.
在Headington附近有个建材场
- 看起来奥赛罗没戏了
Looks like Othello's in the clear.
Right. Fetch the car round.
- 好了 把车开过来吧
Mrs Madison's niece know anything
about this Nimmo character?
Madison太太的侄女知道这个什么Nimmo吗?
No, sir.
See if you can run him down.
- 不知道 长官
- 看看能不能查到他在哪
Find out what he was doing there.
- 在那里干什么
What about this builder?
- 那建材场怎么办?
Balfours几个月前装修过浴室
The Balfours had a bathroom suite
installed a few months back.
恰好就在她"看望病母"的那段时间
Round about the time she was
"visiting her sick mother".
Let's just say I'd be
very surprised
我敢说
if it wasn't Roy Adamson's building
firm that was doing the work.
要不是Roy Adamson的建筑公司揽的活就怪了
下午好 我是警察
Oh. Good afternoon. City Police.
I'm looking for a Mister Nimmo.
I believe he lives at number 8.
我找Nimmo先生 好像住在8号
从来没见过他
I've never seen him.
How long have you lived here?
Nearly three years.
- 你住在这里多久了
- 3年
Oh.
Well, thank you for your help.
好吧 谢谢你的协助
- 但是听到过他
Heard him, though.
You've heard him?
- 你听到过他的声音?
Music blaring out till all hours.
一天到晚音乐震天响
I've written to the landlord.
Not that it's made no difference.
我给房东写信投诉过 没用
- 哪种类型音乐?
- 古典乐
What kind of music?
Classical.
特别可怕 唱歌
You know, bloody awful stuff.
Singing.
猫叫春似的
Well, caterwauling.
谢谢你
Thank you.
没错 我们的确给Balfour先生做过事
Yeah, we did some work for
Mister Balfour.
There you go. A bathroom suite.
Pink.
找到了 粉红色浴室
A few months back.
- 几个月前的事儿了
What did you make of 'em?
- 你对他们有什么看法吗?
没看法 就普通客户
I didn't make anything of 'em.
Just customers.
- 人很好
- 最近见过他们吗?
Nice enough.
Seen 'em recently?
No. Not since the job finished.
完工后就再没见过
- 你确定吗?
- 确定
You sure about that?
Pretty sure.
See, the thing is, Roy...
事情是这样的 Roy...
We found Mrs Balfour strangled
yesterday.
Balfour太太昨天被勒死了
而她手提包上有你的指纹
And your fingerprints have
turned up on her handbag.
Anything you'd like to
tell me about that?
你有什么话要说我听听吗?
去那间
That's you.
快点 快进去
Go on, in you get.
He's admitted carrying on with her.
Not that he had much choice.
他承认跟她有关系 不过也是不得已才承认的
Sergeant Jakes found an earring in
the footwell of a works' truck.
Jakes警长在卡车前面放脚的地方
发现了一只耳环
A match?
是她的吗?
他说他带她去了Boar山的停车场
Took her up Boar's Hill, he says.
Car park.
Brings her back after by Osney,
where he found her.
后来又把她带回到他找到她的地方 Osney
当时人应该还活着
Alive and well, presumably.
DeBryn医生找你 长官 是今早的"突然死亡"案
Call for you, sir. Dr DeBryn.
The "sudden" this morning.
毒物学检测出来了
Pending toxicological results,
I consulted a colleague from
the Botanic Gardens.
我咨询了一个植物园的朋友
He identified the leaves
in the teapot
他说茶壶里的植物是曼陀罗叶
as having come from Datura
stramonium.
Datura?
A weed.
- 曼陀罗?
- 一种野草
也叫"刺苹果"或者"恶魔的诱惑"
Also known as the Thorn Apple,
or Devil's Snare.
- 有毒?
- 毒性很高
Poisonous?
Oh, highly toxic.
The seed pods in particular.
I took the liberty.
我就查了一下本草纲目
Been used for centuries
by the Indians and Chinese
中国和印度用这种药治疗哮喘
已经几世纪了
as a treatment for asthma.
但药与毒药之分 在用量上只有些微差别
But the line between a medicinal and
a lethal dose is very thin indeed.
Contains atropine and scopolamine.
里头含有阿托品和莨菪碱
The "truth" drug.
That's right.
- 是"吐真剂"吧
- 没错
Taken in overdose, symptoms include
severe hallucinations, seizures.
如果服用过量就会出现严重的幻觉 痉挛
然后渐渐失明
All leading, step by jolly step,
to blindness, coma
and an eventual "how do you do"
from St Peter.
昏迷 最终死亡
如果有人上瘾的话
If one goes in for that sort of
thing.
你怎么看Madison太太的死?
What do you make to it? Mrs Madison.
为钱?
Money?
With only a niece and nephew living,
I'd expect they stand to inherit.
只有一个侄子一个侄女
估计不会不要遗产吧
- 那个Nimmo呢?
- 没人在家见过他
What about your Mister Nimmo?
No-one's seen him around his flat.
But a neighbour said he had music
blaring till all hours.
但是有邻居说他音乐开得震耳欲聋
Opera, by the sound of it.
听起来像是歌剧
The entire lease on his lodgings is
conducted through a solicitor.
他房屋租赁通过律师代办的
They're running down a cheque.
他们现在在追查支票
应该能通过银行查到个更可靠的地址
Should be able to get a more
reliable address from his bank.
A weed, Dr DeBryn said.
DeBryn医生说是一种药草
不可能是她自己种的呀?
Not likely to be something she'd
have been cultivating, is it?
I wouldn't have thought so.
是啊 不可能
There's something about Datura
I can't quite put my finger on.
曼陀罗的事我说不上来
至少Balfour的案子是有点儿眉目了
At least the Balfour case looks
like it's going to run to form.
The builder? Has he confessed?
那个建筑商? 他认罪了?
Not yet. I'm letting him sweat
for the minute.
还没 但是我先让他担惊受怕一下
I'll have another go after lunch.
我午饭后再去问问
还没 但是我先让他担惊受怕一下
Speaking of which...
我午饭后再去问问
说到这个...
Now, let's see.
What have I got to look forward to?
Luncheon meat.
哈 我来猜猜今天带的是什么三明治?
Remind me never to spend Christmas
at your house.
午餐肉
"Ici... loin du monde reel."
记得提醒我永远别去你家过圣诞
- 那是Lakme唱的最后一句 长官
- 谁?
They're the last words sung
by Lakme, sir. Whom?
Lakme 长官 一个印度公主 德利布歌剧的女英雄
Lakme, sir. An Indian princess.
The heroine of an opera by Delibes.
根据Morse所说 这个剧里的姑娘Lakme
According to Morse, sir,
this Lakme girl kills herself
by eating leaves from the
Datura plant.
是吃了曼陀罗叶子自杀的
跟毒死Grace Madison的是同一种植物
The same as was used to poison
Grace Madison.
Makes it two, sir.
这样就有两起了 长官
What makes two? Two deaths, sir.
With a connection to opera.
- 什么两起?
- 两起和歌剧有关的死亡
There was a phrase from... What is
it? Otello, sir. By Giuseppe Verdi.
- 有句歌词... 什么剧目来着?
- 奥赛罗 长官 是朱塞佩·威尔第的剧目
Chalked on the door of the goods
wagon where we found Evelyn Balfour.
用粉笔写在Evelyn Balfour死亡的车厢门上的
"再吻一次" Morse说是他最后的台词
"One kiss more."
His last words, Morse says.
你说的是莎士比亚的奥赛罗? 那个黑人?
You mean Shakespeare's Othello?
The blackamoor?
- 没错
- Evelyn Balfour是被勒死的
That's him, sir, yes.
Evelyn Balfour was strangled, sir,
跟奥赛罗的太太Desdemona死法一样
like Desdemona, Othello's wife.
而且她口中还塞了一条手帕
A handkerchief was stuffed
in her mouth,
embroidered with the initial D.
上面绣有字母D
I thought we had someone for the
Balfour killing.
Balfour案子不是抓到人了吗?
好了Morse 出去吧
All right, Morse. As you were.
Opera? Good God!
歌剧? 老天呐!
A man would have to be
some sort of raving lunatic
to go to such lengths.
人是得有多疯才能想到这种解释
如果他是疯子的话 也是个聪明的疯子
If he is a lunatic, sir, I'd have
to say he's a very clever one.
If you have no objection,
如果你不反对的话
I'd like to second Morse from
General Duties for the duration.
我想让Morse这段时间调岗来查案
有这个必要吗?
Is that necessary?
Specialist knowledge, sir -
it comes to this sort of thing.
遇到歌剧这类问题 长官
我们需要他的知识
好吧 但是只有这一个案子
Very well. But for the duration
of the inquiry only.
- 我不希望他有什么想法
I don't want him getting ideas.
That's kind of what I'm counting on.
- 我还有点指望靠他破这案呢
知道了 长官
Sir.
Usual time in the morning, is it?
明天早上老时间?
不用了  Morse可以来接我
No, you're all right.
Morse can fetch me.
你暂时不用值班了
You're off General Duties till
further notice.
8.15 sharp. All right?
8点15整 知道了吗?
Morse.
Morse
Hello?
你好?
见过这个没?
Seen this?
Late Edition.
最近出的
How the hell have they come by that?
"Reliable sources", I expect.
- 他们是怎么编出来的?
- "可靠消息来源"吧我猜
- 你不是说真的吧?
- 这么说吧 伙计
Are you serious?
Put it this way, matey.
For a bloke who puts it away
the way he does,
Jakes能够放下身段
Jakes is never anything less
than flush, is he?
还怎么可能不春风得意呢 对吧
算了 让他去吧
Anyroad. Get 'em in, then.
我想我们可以讨论下Fitton的案子
I thought we might have a go
through the Fitton's.
不然你过不了警长考试的
You'll never get your Sergeant's,
otherwise.
如果你不介意的话 我先走了
I was gonna push off,
if it's all the same.
It's your round.
I'll owe you one.
- 这次轮到你请客
- 先欠着
Right.
好吧
I don't suppose your aunt
我估计你婶婶
没跟你哥哥提过Nimmo先生吧?
might have mentioned this Mr Nimmo
to your brother?
She may. But, if she did, he never
told me.
可能吧 但是也可能他没跟我提过
我...我想跟他谈谈
I'd er... I'd like to
speak with him.
I'm afraid he's very busy
at the moment.
可是他现在很忙
Of course.
没事
等他有空再说
At his convenience.
Well, good night. I'm sorry to have
troubled you, Miss Madison.
那晚安了 抱歉打扰你 Madison小姐
呃 早...
Uh...
爸!
Dad!
Well, don't stand on ceremony.
怎么 还不进来?
It's probably best if I
wait in the car.
我还是在车里等吧
It's probably best
if you just do as you're told.
我觉得你最好还是听我的
You've come in, then. I'm impressed.
你还是进来了啊 真了不起
老爸的手下一般等上6个月才进得来
Most of Pop's it takes
at least six months.
That lump is my brother Sam.
You want a cuppa?
那个笨蛋是我哥哥Sam 要来杯茶吗?
- 谢谢 我不用了 Thursday小姐
No, I'm fine, thanks,
Miss Thursday. Miss Thursday!
Thursday小姐!
- 她在银行里老被这么叫都腻了
She gets enough of that
down the bank.
Start calling her it at home
and she'll get airs.
在家里听见有人这么叫她会生气的
That's Joan, love.
It's one of Dad's, Mum.
- 她叫Joan 亲爱的
- 妈 他是老爸手下
我可没觉得他是足球场来的
I didn't think he was
from the pools.
Sit yourself down.
He won't be a tick.
坐吧 他马上就好
那么
So.
- 你叫什么?
What do they call you, then?
- Morse
Morse.
Morse? Morse什么?
Morse? Morse what?
Morse电码啊 滴滴答!
Morse Code. Dit-dit-dah!
You still here, Joan?
Morning, sir.
- 你还没走呢 Joan?
- 早上好 长官
I thought it was twenty-past,
your bus. I'm just going.
- 你不是20分的车吗?
- 我就走
Sam 出门前把垃圾桶拿出去
Sam, fetch the bins out
before you go to work.
别让你妈弄
Don't leave it to your mother.
好了 我们走了
Right. We're off.
给 都准备好了吧
Here, let's have a look at you.
要平安回家啊
Come home safe.
There, then, you'll do, Fred.
走吧 一路小心 Fred
It went well this morning?
早上顺利吗?
You haven't said.
I don't want to talk about it.
- 你还没说呢
- 我不想讨论这个
但是的确有帮助
But it's helping.
Phillip?
昨晚那个警察来干什么?
What did that policeman want
last night?
我告诉你了 他在调查Grace婶婶的案子
I told you. He's investigating
what happened to Aunt Grace.
他为什么要来家里?
Why did he come to the house?
I don't like people coming
to the house.
我不喜欢别人来家里
他问我一个叫Nimmo的人
He was asking about someone
called Nimmo -
好像是个记者
a journalist of some sort.
Yeah?
进来
银行那边查到Nimmo先生地址了
在一个叫Drover's Rest的地方
The bank's come through with an
address for Mr Nimmo, sir.
Some place called Drover's Rest.
- 好的
- Thursday 介绍下 这位是Daniel Cronyn医生
Good.
Thursday, this is Dr Daniel Cronyn.
Cronyn医生 这位是Thursday督察
Dr Cronyn, Detective Inspector
Thursday.
- 你好
- Cronyn医生是一位执业精神病医生
How do you do? Dr Cronyn is a
psychiatrist in private practice.
他对这种精神错乱的人做了一系列研究
He's made a particular study of
these kind of deranged individuals.
希望他的专业意见能帮到你们
You might benefit from his
professional opinion.
这类案件的行凶者
The perpetrator of these crimes
明显有很严重的心理失常
clearly exhibits a profoundly
disturbed psyche.
可不是
Indeed.
我想这些你们都知道
I'm sure I'm not telling you
anything you don't know.
What may be less obvious
to you, perhaps,
你们也许会忽略的是
is that he will also be
highly functioning.
他效率会很高
我很遗憾的说 这使得你们很难抓住他
Which, I regret to say, will make
him very difficult to apprehend.
But not impossible?
- 但还是有机会?
Such cases are few and
far between over here,
- 谢天谢地 在英国此类案件很少
但我美国同事
but my colleagues in the
United States
believe this kind of killer is
something of a coming trend.
认为这类凶手是一种未来趋势
A trend?
Indeed.
- 趋势?
- 没错
比如过去十年里的Starkweather案
Within the last ten years we've had
the Starkweather case,
尸体被丢弃在波士顿
the bodies in the swamp at Fairvale
Fairvale和DeSalvo的沼泽地
and DeSalvo in Boston.
What's he after? What's behind him?
Impossible to say.
- 他追求什么? 为什么这么做?
- 很难说
除了他符合几年前McDonald提出的
Other than he conforms to the
triad personality
黑暗三性格的假设
of Narcissism, Machiavellianism
and Psychopathy
posited by McDonald
a couple of years back,
自恋者 心理变态者 权谋者
我会认为他是个很聪明的人
I'd expect him to be highly
intelligent.
虽然这不代表他一定会在学术上有所成就
Though this may not necessarily be
reflected in academic achievements.
- 他多大?
- 25岁到35岁 最多40
How old?
Mid-20s to mid-30s. 40 at a push.
还有继续作案的可能?
There's no possibility this
could be the end of it?
Gentlemen, you're confronting
a mind...
先生们 你们要抓的是个...
unconstrained by notions
of guilt...
不知内疚...
悔恨 对与错...
regret, right and wrong...
善与恶的人
good and evil.
So far as he's concerned,
we're just... prey.
对他来说 我们只是猎物
Prey?
猎物?
In his eyes.
在他眼里
Kine...
牛群的存在...
reared to slaughter.
为的是被宰杀
We'll stop him.
我们会阻止他的
How? You think you're
going to appeal
怎么阻止? 你觉得你能唤醒
to his nobler instincts,
his better angels?
他的天性和善良的一面?
他没有这些
He doesn't have any.
The only thing I can tell you with
absolute certainty...
我只能肯定地告诉你...
is he will kill again.
他还会再行凶
下午好
Good afternoon.
Afternoon.
We're looking for Drover's Rest.
Some sort of farm, I believe.
我们在找Drover's Rest 应该是个农场
Slaughteryard.
屠宰场
Old Ben Nimmo's place.
老Ben Nimmo家的
Mr Nimmo wouldn't be a journalist,
then?
Nimmo不是记者吧?
除非他写的是宠物食品
Not unless he writes about pet food.
明白了
I see.
能给我们指个路吗?
Could you point us in the right
direction?
- 你们找老Ben做什么?
- 办案
What d'you want with Old Ben, then?
Police business.
郡警局的
City Police.
- 离这远吗?
Are we far?
You've come past the turning
about two mile.
- 两英里之前就该拐弯了
Well, thank you, Mr...?
好吧 谢谢你 怎么称呼?
Oakshott. Lemuel.
Lemuel Oakshott
You won't find him there.
你找不到他的
Gone away.
搬走了
他老婆Ada死后就没见过他
I haven't seen him since Ada died,
his wife.
估计去他儿子那里了
Gone to his boy, maybe.
Canada.
在加拿大
Mr Nimmo?
Nimmo先生?
砸门
Take it down.
You go up there, I'll go down here.
你去上面 我去下面
是歌剧阿依达里的 长官
It's from Aida, sir.
Radames最后的咏叹调
Radames' final aria.
就在他被活埋之前唱的
Just before he's entombed alive.
Cement mixer in the yard,
wasn't there?
院子里有个混凝土搅拌器是吧?
那个看着像新的
That looks new.
We've had a patrol round this
flat leased in Nimmo's name,
the one you went to.
我们派人去Nimmo租住的地方巡查了
就是你去的地方
Nothing there but a record player
and a stack of LPs.
除了播放器和唱片啥也没有
It's not been occupied
so far as the lads can tell.
小伙子们说那里一直没人住
估计也是
I didn't think it would've been.
Look sharp, then, Morse. It's the
competition.
要快点啊Morse 这是比赛
Somebody with even more crackpot
ideas than you.
居然有人比你还疯狂
Buried alive?
活埋?
Nothing quite so quick, I'm afraid.
致命速度不快
This was immurement.
Walling up.
是埋在墙壁里面的
Cause of death would have been more
likely dehydration than asphyxia.
死亡原因可能不是窒息而是脱水
- 多久?
- 好几天吧
How long?
For some days.
My God!
天呐!
然后身体器官开始慢慢衰竭...
Then as the organs of the body
began to fail...
精神失常...
delirium...
madness.
发疯
One can only pray his heart
gave out first.
只求一死
Would you excuse me?
抱歉
这其中有蹊跷 Morse
There's wickedness in this, Morse.
I can understand gain, jealousy,
revenge, even.
我能理解为财 嫉妒或报仇下毒手
But killing just for the sheer hell
of it?
但是单纯为杀人而杀人?
这还是头一次见
That's something new.
你好 牛津邮报 有什么可以帮你?
Hello, Oxford Mail.
How can I help you?
What's this?
这是什么?
死者身上找到的 长官
Found on the victim, sir.
歌剧日本天皇 KoKo的歌
It's from The Mikado, KoKo's song.
"As someday it may happen
that a victim might be found".
"也许有一天会有一个受害者"
我想他觉得那样有趣吧??
I suppose he thinks that's funny.
It's also known as The List Song,
sir.
- 它也叫名单歌长官
- 名单歌?
List?
KoKo是Mikado的行刑队主管
KoKo was the Lord High Executioner
to the Mikado.
He read a list of society offenders
he said he was going to execute.
他宣读他说要被处死的犯人的名单
The chorus runs,
合唱部分是
"他们在名单上 没有一个人可以逃过"
"He's got 'em on the list
and they'll none of 'em be missed"
就是我们的3个死者吧
Our three victims, presumably.
How many more has he got in mind?
That's what worries me.
他还想杀几个人? 这才是我担心的
长官 你来这边看看
Something you should see, sir.
Through here.
You too, Morse.
你也是 Morse
看起来你有崇拜者了
Looks like you've got an admirer.
Nimmo的口袋里有一张曲谱
There was a musical score
stuffed in Mr Nimmo's pockets.
The List Song, apparently.
叫名单歌
Doctor?
No.
- 怎么了医生?
- 没事
我只是瞬间觉得...
For a moment, I...
But it can't be. I'm just...
但不可能 我只是...
There was a... a patient.
我以前有个病人
50年代初 我在拜洛沃疗养院疗
I met him in the early '50s,
Elias医生手下工作时遇到的
when I was working at Bellevue
Sanatorium under Dr Elias.
他当时20岁左右
He'd have been about 20 then.
叫什么?
Who would?
A young man called... Miller.
一个年轻人...叫Miller
Keith Miller
Keith Miller.
他算是个音乐神童
He was some sort of musical
child prodigy.
据大家说他很聪明
Quite brilliant, by all accounts.
But on the morning of his
15th birthday,
但是15岁生日那天的早上
he took an axe from the
woodshed and...
他从木棚里拿了一把斧头...
buried it in the back of
his mother's skull.
砍在了他母亲的脑袋上
他后来怎么样了?
What happened to him?
"有罪但患有精神病"
"Guilty but insane".
He was sentenced to be detained
at His Majesty's Pleasure.
他被关起来等候女王发落
What makes you think he's connected?
你为什么觉得他和这个案子有关?
When he was in therapy,
治疗期间
he described horribly violent,
murderous fantasies -
他描述了他也许会对那些工作人员
惹怒他的工作人员所下的毒手的幻想
what he would and wouldn't like to
do to various members of staff
who'd rubbed him up the wrong way.
暴力而残忍的幻想
It was a pet phrase of his.
他的口头禅是
"我有个名单"
"I've got a little list."
Where is he now?
他现在在哪?
I seem to remember a colleague
saying he'd been released, cured...
我记得有个同事说差不多五六年前
他痊愈释放了...
about five or six years ago.
问题是...
The point is...
he was an Oxford boy.
他是牛津人
- 情况不妙啊 Thursday
- 是的 长官
Bad ju-ju, Thursday.
Yes, sir.
快点查清楚 就指望你了 Morse!
Get to the bottom of it and quick.
I'm relying on you. Morse!
You're off General Duties because
I'm told this is your area.
你调来查这件案子
是因为有人说你对歌剧懂行
看你怎么证明自己有用了
See you prove yourself useful.
Sir.
是的 长官
All right, Morse?
怎么了 Morse?
他的墙上为什么有我的照片?
Why has he got my picture
on the wall?
It just tickled his fancy.
I wouldn't read too much into it.
他觉得好玩吧 你别想太多
- 他只是想让我们乱阵脚
- 还挺有用啊
He's just trying to get us rattled.
It's working.
Then, don't let it.
I need you thinking straight.
那就别让他得逞 你得思路清晰才行
11点左右送来的
It was delivered around 11.
?3-OCPO
"?: 3 - OCP: 0."
这是指我们牛津郡警局吧
That's us, I suppose,
Oxford City Police.
Three-nil to the Opera Phantom.
剧院魅影杀手3:0领先
我是这么觉得的 又有人死了?
That was rather my reading of it.
There's been another one?
Actually, Miss Frazil, I'd urge you
in the strongest possible terms
Frazil小姐 我非常强烈建议你
not to make this communication
known to the public.
不要把这样的内容公布于众
就当帮忙
As a favour.
This person we're after is clearly
working to some sort of plan.
我们要抓的这个人显然计划周全
我希望你同意不要发表这些信息
I'd hope by your agreeing
not to publish,
就算我们不能打乱他的计划
we might derail whatever scheme
he's got in mind
至少可以拖延一下
or delay it, at least.
24 hours.
24小时
After that...
Pray that's enough.
- 过后...
- 希望时间够用
Morse
Morse.
我听到了
I heard it.
Put your sandals on, then.
把鞋穿上吧
每个...好...孩子...
Every... Good... Boy...
Deserves Favours.
都该爱护
I've spoken to Bellevue, sir.
我和拜洛沃疗养院通过话 长官
Seems there was a fire there,
three years ago,
貌似三年前那里起了一场大火
连同档案室一起
destroyed several wings of
the sanatorium,
together with the records office.
烧掉了好几间疗养院的房间
Surely if this happened locally...?
如果这是本地事件...?
我们这里没相关档案 我已经向郡里提请调档了
Nothing on our files, sir.
I've put in a request to County.
- 长官...
- 我们的常驻专家来了
Sir...
Ah! Our resident expert.
Opera!
歌剧!
我觉得凶手不是随意选择被害人的 长官
I don't think the killer's
choosing his victims at random.
There may be a pattern.
A pattern?
- 好像有规律
- 规律?
To the killings.
I can't be sure, but...
杀人的规律 我不能肯定 但是...
Every Good Boy Deserves Favour.
Every what?
- 每个好孩子都该爱护
- 每个什么?
这是高音谱号上音符的助记码
It's a mnemonic for remembering
the notes on a treble clef.
每个好孩子都该爱护
Every Good Boy Deserves Favour -
EGBDF
EGBDF.
Evelyn Grace Ben
Evelyn, Grace, Ben.
That it?
是那个?
So the next one will start with a D.
那下一个受害者名字是以D开头的
Debbie?
Debbie!
Debbie Snow, sir. Six years old.
Debbie Snow 长官 今年六岁
Taken from the street outside
her house.
从自家门口被人绑走
形貌特征已经发给各个巡逻警员了
Description's been circulated
to all cars and foot patrols.
- 是他
- 不能这么武断
It's him.
We can't say that.
- 不能只因为她的名字以D开头就这么断定
- 不止这些 长官
Just because her name begins with
a D. There's more than that, sir.
The translator from Lonsdale
identified the score
经Lonsdale学院的译员鉴定
sent to Miss Frazil as
Snegurochka by Rimsky-Korsakov.
寄给Frazil小姐的乐谱
是里姆斯基·科萨科夫的Snegurochka
Snegurochka is Russian for
Snowmaiden.
Snegurochka在俄语中是雪姑娘的意思
想必这歌剧里有人死了吧
Somebody dies, presumably.
死的是雪姑娘自己
她在黎明来临时融化了
The Snowmaiden herself.
She melts at dawn.
- 就在太阳升起之时
As the sun rises.
Something stuffed down in the toe,
according to Uniform.
- 员警说鞋尖里有东西
"No alibi err badly."
What the hell does that mean?
"无不在场证明 大错特错"
这什么鸟意思?
Maybe he's saying we've made
a mistake, sir.
也许他的意思是我们犯了错误 长官
我们正在调查的某人涉及其他谋杀案件
One of the people we've seen in
relation to the other killings.
某个没有不在场证明的人 或是...
Someone without an alibi, or...
"Near by Libra idol"?
"就在天秤座雕像的旁边"?
Some kind of direction, perhaps?
也许是指示方向的?
- 他是想测试我们
- 什么测试?
He's setting us a test.
What sort of test?
It's a game.
这是个游戏
Solve the puzzle, save the child.
解决谜题就能救出孩子
"Near by Libra idol"?
"就在天秤座雕像的旁边"?
Libra is the Scales, sir. Justice,
maybe?
天秤座就是天平 长官 也许代表公正?
The idol could be a statue
by the Law Courts.
雕像可能是法院旁边那座
Think you can you crack it?
I can try.
- 你能破解吗?
- 我可以试试
Try?
试?
You need to do more than try.
All right, Jakes. That'll do.
- 你可不能只是试试
- 行了 Jakes 这就够了
他不是所谓的专家吗?
Meant to be the expert, isn't he?
Laughing-boy's pin-up.
I said, that'll do.
- 中看不中用?
- 我说 够了
I'm thinking of the kiddie, sir.
我在担心那个孩子 长官
Us turning on each other's
going to help find her, is it?
Exactly what he wants.
我们起内讧对找到她有帮助吗?
他就想看到我们出乱子
It's Morse these messages are meant
for, sir. We all know that.
这些信息是专门给Morse的 长官
我们都清楚这点
He's seen his picture in the paper.
他在报纸上见过他的照片
- 该死的疯子一家亲
One bloody misfit talking
to another.
- 管好你自己的事 警长
About your business, Sergeant.
He's right. If I can't crack this...
他说得对 如果我破解不了这个...
It's not all on you, Morse,
whatever Sergeant Jakes says.
不管Jakes警长说什么
这都不是你一个人的事 Morse
雪姑娘在黎明就要融化了 长官
The Snowmaiden melts, sir... at dawn.
However he intends to bring that
about, by fire...
他想怎么动手 用火还是...
- 我们只剩不到12小时找到她了
We've less than 12 hours to find
her.
Then we'd better get a move on.
- 那我们最好开始找起来
我是Morse
Morse.
Where is she?
她在哪?
"天秤座雕像"
"Libra idol."
我真笨!
Fool!
你好先生 我是郡警局的Morse警员
Hello, sir. Detective Constable
Morse. City Police.
I'd like to know if anyone's
requested the score
我想知道是否有人借过
里姆斯基·科萨科夫的雪姑娘的乐谱
for The Snow Maiden.
Rimsky-Korsakov.
Is that the Western Score?
Mm.
- 是西方经典吗?
- 对
Give me a moment.
稍等
对 没错 上个月17日从书库里取出来的
Yes, indeed, it was brought up
from the stacks
on the 17th of last month for Mr
Miller.
是一位Miller先生借阅的
Miller?
Keith Miller?
That's right.
是的
他常来这里看书吗?
Is he a regular reader?
This last year, yes, indeed.
As a matter of fact,
最近这一年是的 事实上
a fresh set of scores have
just been delivered to him.
我们刚给他送去了几部新乐谱
He's here now?
- 他现在在这?
- 他差不多15分钟前来的
He arrived not quarter
of an hour ago.
- 关了图书馆
- 你说什么?
Close the library.
I beg your pardon?
I need you to seal the building.
把整座大楼封锁起来
包括门窗以及逃生通道
Doors. Windows. Fire escape.
I don't have the authority.
- 我没有这个权限
I'm a police officer.
- 我是警察
That's all the authority you need.
这个权限就足够了
一个孩子的生命危在旦夕 拜托你
A child's life stands in the
balance. Please.
Crane小姐 能麻烦你和Thornhill小姐
关闭图书馆吗?
Miss Crane, will you and Miss
Thornhill close the library?
- 关闭图书馆 Straker先生?
- 嘘
Close it, Mr Straker?
Ssh.
请你安静快速地关馆
Quickly and quietly, if you please.
- 读者怎么办?
- 待在室内
What about the readers?
They're to remain inside.
He's from the police.
Step lively, now.
他是警方的人 快点
Ah... He's gone.
啊...他走了
He was sitting there.
他刚才还坐这呢
你看见刚才坐在这的那人去哪了吗?
The man who was sitting here,
did you see where he went?
这边
This way.
- 从这能出去吗?
- 从上边是不行的
Is there a way out from here?
Not up there, no.
如果他下楼去了 你就抓不到他了
And you won't get him if he's
gone down into the stacks.
There's five storeys underground.
地下一共有五层
The corridors go for miles.
走廊延伸好几里呢
What about exits?
The bicycle chain.
- 出口呢?
- 用自行车链锁着
A pulley railway under the Broad.
通到Broad街下面的滑轮铁路
Call 999. Tell them DC Morse
from Cowley Station
打电话报警 就说Cowley分局的Morse警员
needs immediate assistance
at the Bodleian.
急需支援 叫他们来Bodleian图书馆
Police. Leave. Now.
警察 快出去 快
Argh!
Morse?
- Morse?
- 你看到他吗? 他往哪跑的?
Did you see him?
Which way did he go?
See who?
Him! The suspect!
- 看到谁?
- 他啊! 嫌犯啊!
你没事吧 伙计?
You all right, matey?
Huh?
Your shirt...
- 嗯?
- 你的衬衫...
这边 有人受伤了!
Over here, man down!
没事伙计 坚持住伙计
All right, mate. You're OK, matey.
Don't just stand there,
get some help!
别傻站着 叫人来帮忙啊!
All right, matey.
没事了 伙计
- 联系警局
- 好的
Ring the station.
Right.
Morse 我要帮你压住这里 准备好了吗?
Morse, I am going to put some
pressure on this, all right?
I know, mate, I know. I know.
好了 伙计 好了 好了
Not too deep. Thankfully.
还好伤口不深
But a clean cut like that'll be
a bugger to knit.
但切得这么平整的伤口愈合起来可不容易
It's far better gashing yourself
on something jagged.
砍成锯齿状的伤口长起来比较方便
I'll bear that in mind next time
I chase a lunatic under the Bodleian.
下次去Bodleian图书馆下面追疯子
我一定牢牢记住这点
你怎么会去那的?
What led you there?
An anagram. Well, double anagram.
回文构词法 确切地说
是双重回文构词法
"No alibi err badly Near by libra idol"
"No alibi err badly.
Near by libra idol."
- 这两句话用的是同样的字母
Both phrases use the same letters.
- Bodleian Library(牛津大学主图书馆)
Bodleian Library.
- 干杯!
- 祝你健康 毋庸置疑!
Cheers!
Your health, surely!
It's going to be tight and quite
tender for the next few days.
接下来几天伤口会觉得有点紧且容易痛
所以 卧床休息
So... bed rest.
And my finest Broderie Anglaise
notwithstanding,
虽然伤口我缝得很好
don't exert yourself overmuch.
你还是悠着点
The girl's still missing. I've got
to get back.
小姑娘还没找到 我得回去工作
Morse...
Morse
If he'd decided to stab
and not to slash,
如果他当时不是划你一刀而是直接捅的话
我现在就对你的五脏六腑非常熟悉了
I'd presently be getting
more acquainted with your anatomy
那是我俩都不乐意看到的
than either of us might care for.
Soon as not be heaving your tripes
into a tray, if it's all the same.
还要让你的器官不堆积在盘子里
如果你不介意的话
Not just yet at least.
至少现在先别工作
Uniform recovered this lot from a
bin on Catte Street by the library.
警察在图书馆边的Catte街上的
一个垃圾桶里发现了这些
Another one of those score things
here.
又是一本乐谱
"有些警察不长脑
"Some coppers have no brains.
所有警察是混球"
All coppers are bastards."
I want it back,
clean, starched and pressed.
衬衫还我的时候
得洗干净 上好浆 熨平展
You sure you're fit for duty?
你确定你还能继续工作?
是啊 感觉没看上去那么糟
Yeah. It looks much worse
than it feels.
- 我错过了什么?
What did I miss?
- 找到开冰激凌车的人了
The Ice Cream Man's been found.
他觉得 只是觉得
He thinks - only thinks, mind -
他看到一个符合Debbie描述的女孩
跟一个男人讲话
he saw a girl answering Debbie's
description talking to a man.
Beard. Glasses.
有胡子 戴眼镜
拄着手杖
Walking stick.
它是Bocardo式的三段论
It's a Modus Bocardo syllogism.
A category of logical argument.
逻辑论证的一种论式
Two propositions, one major,
one minor,
两个命题 一个大前提 一个小前提
and the "therefore" symbol
is the clue.
这个"所以"符号是线索
"Some coppers have no brains.
All coppers are bastards.
"有些警察不长脑 所有警察是混球"
所以有些混球不长脑
Therefore some bastards
have no brains."
It has to be more than that.
肯定不止这样
He has to give us a sporting chance.
Else, where's the fun in it?
他得给我们个公平的机会
不然乐趣在哪呢?
Well, whatever it means,
不管它是什么意思
as an exercise in bamboozling
the police, it's brilliant.
作为迷惑警方的手段 它还挺有才的
I doubt Debbie Snow would see it
that way.
- Debbie Snow可不会这么觉得
- 对你真的很重要是吧?
It really matters to you,
doesn't it?
找到这个姑娘
Finding this girl.
我是说 我也很想找到她
你别误会我
I mean, it matters to me.
Don't get me wrong.
But with you it's...
但对你而言...
- 你为什么要做警察?
- 我们不是来谈我的事的
Why did you become a policeman?
We're not here to talk about me.
If you've nothing else to add...
如果你没什么发现的话...
In my experience,
a policeman's need to save people
就我的经验来看
警察拯救别人的需求
是典型地源于要拯救某一个人的需求
is typically born of a need
to save one person.
Who couldn't you save,
Constable Morse?
- 你没能拯救谁 Morse警员?
- 晚安 医生
Good night, Doctor.
不管他在玩什么鬼把戏
这个姑娘都是他的"素材"
The girl is "materiel" in whatever
diabolical game he's playing.
The real object here is to prove
whose intellect is the greater.
此刻他真正的目的是想证明谁更聪明
目前 它...
So far, it's...
You admire him.
你钦佩他
算是尊重吧
Respect, perhaps.
他的能力 他明确的目标
His ability.
His singularity of purpose.
- 什么目标?
- 他生而为杀
Which is?
He lives to kill.
他吃饭 睡觉 杀人 这就是他的全部
He eats. He sleeps. He kills.
That's all he does.
他对他受害者的同情
With no more sympathy
for his victims
than you would feel
in taking a paper to a wasp.
绝不会比你拍死黄蜂时的多
那他为什么不杀我?
Then why didn't he kill me?
因为他愿意让你活着
Because it suits him to
have you alive.
我们抓不到他的
We're not going to make it.
Are we?
是吧?
Bocardo.
Bocardo
Bocardo Prison...
Bocardo监狱...
Morse
Morse.
凶手设的谜是Bocardo式逻辑三段论
The riddle the killer set
was a Bocardo syllogism.
Bocardo?
That's the key.
- Bocardo?
- 这是关键
The word Bocardo, not the syllogism.
Bocardo这个词 不是三段论
我知道牛津有个地方和Bocardo有关
I knew there was a Bocardo
connection to Oxford
可是想不起来 一直到刚才
我路过Broad街的纪念塔时才想起来
but I couldn't place it until
I passed the Memorial on the Broad.
殉道纪念塔?
The Martyrs' memorial?
Prior to being burnt at the stake,
all three were in the Bocardo Prison.
先前火刑上烧死的
三名囚犯都来自Bocardo监狱
在牛津? 没听说过啊
In Oxford? Never heard of it.
以前在北门圣米迦勒堂边上
It used to stand here
by St Michael at the North Gate.
The Martyrs' cell door is on
display in the Church Tower.
殉道纪念塔的牢门还在教堂塔里展出
- 是吧?
- 是的 长官
Right?
Yes, sir.
Get it open.
快打开
Oh...
You're going to be all right.
你会没事的
- 谢谢你
- 拜拜
Thank you.
Bye-bye.
什么时候的事? 完毕
When was this? Over.
Morse?
- 噢不用了 谢谢
- 得了 伙计
Oh, no thanks.
Come on, matey.
吃饱睡足 回头又是一条好汉
A full belly and a few hours' kip,
you'll be right as nine-pence.
It was too easy.
- 这太容易了
Not how I heard it.
- 我可不是这么听说的
It doesn't make any sense.
这完全说不通
照他的游戏规则 这说不通
Not if he's playing by the rules.
雪姑娘...她融化了
The Snow Maiden... She melts.
Melts? Oh.
融化? 噢
你觉得他是想烧死她 还是...?
You think he meant to
burn her then, or...?
Debbie Snow was never
in any real danger.
Debbie Snow从开始就未涉险
There were air holes in the casket.
因为棺材上有透气孔
No, he was just playing with us.
不对 他只是在耍我们
完毕
Out.
What worries me is why.
让我担心的是原因
- 是Cronyn?
Cronyn?
- 鉴于尸体的腐败状况
Given the condition of the corpus,
我暂时没什么发现
there's not a great deal
I can tell you.
Beyond, of course,
that life is extinct.
当然 除了这人已死之外
Who found the body? Phillip Madison,
sir, and his sister Faye
- 谁发现的尸体?
- Phillip Madison 长官 还有他妹妹Faye
turned up for a nine o'clock session
with the doctor and, well...
他们跟医生预约了九点的治疗 然后... 嗯...
我建议你站远一点 督察
I'd advise you to stand well clear,
Inspector.
- 待我们将它安全塞好再说
Until we can get it safely
stoppered.
- 酸液?
Acid?
Aqua regia by the smell.
凭气味判断是水玻璃
王水
Royal water.
硝基盐酸
(牛津学者合唱协会夏季计划书)
Nitro-hydrochloric acid.
所以他才成了这样
Hence the state of him.
从绿色痕迹来看
容器封口用的是黄铜塞子
From the green tinge, the container
was sealed with a brass bung.
Acid would've eaten through that
in about an hour.
酸液会在一小时内将其腐蚀殆尽
And poured out onto his head.
还倒在他头上
融化 就像雪姑娘
Melted. Like the Snow Maiden.
It wasn't Debbie, it was Daniel.
不是Debbie 是Daniel
Daniel Cronyn.
Daniel Cronyn
EGBD
EGBD.
那我们得赶在凶手之前找到F
Then we need to find whoever F is
before the killer does.
How long had your brother
been seeing Dr Cronyn?
你哥哥在Cronyn医生这看病有多久了?
Four months.
四个月了
Phillip is...
Phillip很...
rather highly strung.
容易精神紧张
The artistic temperament, I suppose.
所谓的艺术家气质吧 大概
We lost our parents, you see.
我们很小的时候就失去了双亲
Quite young.
Phillip took it worst, of course,
being the eldest.
Phillip是长子 所以他承受的最多
He suffers dreadfully
with his nerves.
他的神经让他饱受折磨
我昨晚突然崩溃了
I'd had a bad attack. Yesterday
evening.
I telephoned Dr Cronyn
就打电话给Cronyn医生
and made an appointment
for first thing this morning.
预约了第二天早上看病
我到的时候发现门没锁
When I arrived,
the door was on the latch.
I went in and...
我走进去 然后...
Well, you saw what I found.
你们看到的我就是我看到的
你说他的独奏会快到了是吗
He's a recital coming up, you said.
对 明天
Indeed. Tomorrow.
Will he be in a fit state for that?
- 他这种状态撑得住吗?
This will be his first recital
from memory.
- 我印象中这是他第一次独奏会
但他还是决定继续
But he's determined to go ahead.
For Aunt Grace's sake.
- 为了Grace婶婶
They were close?
- 他们好吗?
非常好
Very.
She and Uncle Cedric had
the raising of us.
她和Cedric叔叔养大了我们
I mean, we boarded in England
most of the year,
我们一年里大部分时间都在英格兰
but we usually summered in Jaipur.
但夏天一般都在Jaipur过
Just for the record, Miss Madison,
where was Phillip last night?
另外要问一下 Madison小姐
Phillip昨晚在哪里?
在家 跟我在一起
At home with me.
谁会做出这么可怕的事情?
Who would do such a terrible thing?
放你出来了啊
Let you out, then.
Small comfort, but if it's any
consolation,
酸液起效的时候
Cronyn医生已经死了 这多少让人好受点
Dr Cronyn was already dead when
the acid did its work.
- 那死因是什么?
So what was the cause?
- 就我的尸检来看
From my examination of him,
他似乎吗啡成瘾
he appears to have been
an habitual morphine addict.
他书桌里有注射器是吧?
There was a syringe in his desk
drawer, wasn't there?
Morse?
Er, yes.
是的
Together with some ampoules
of morphia. Mm-hm.
旁边还有几剂吗啡
说不定有人给他过量吗啡
Somebody gave him an overdose,
maybe,
or slipped something in the syringe
that wasn't morphine.
或者在注射器里混了别的东西进去
Possible, of course.
当然有可能
但是血检结果出来后才能确定
But until I've had his
blood results back...
死亡时间是今早2点至5点之间
Time was between two and five
o'clock this morning.
- 还有别的吗?
- 大体上缺乏良好照顾
Anything else?
General lack of care.
但大都是瘾君子身上的正常现象
But nothing I wouldn't expect to
find in any other addict.
他是个心理医生
And him a doctor of the mind.
Physician, heal thyself.
医者先自医
吗啡
Morphine.
Access wouldn't be a problem
in his line, I don't suppose.
按他的工作性质应该不难搞到手吧
But he didn't strike me as the type.
Did he you?
可我觉得他不是这种人 你说呢?
Morse?
喂!
Oi!
你多久没睡了? 停车
When'd you last get any sleep?
Pull over.
好了 自己找地方坐
Right. Sit yourself down
through there.
- 我没事 长官
- 别跟我争
I'm fine, sir.
Don't argue.
你要累坏了对我就没用了
You're no good to me dead
on your feet.
I'll get a brew on.
我给你倒杯茶
Or there's a drop of brandy
if you like.
还是你要来杯白兰地
还是白兰地好了
Better make it brandy.
什么情况 大下午的居然回家?
What's this,
home in the middle of the afternoon?
- 我带Morse回来 他在那间房里
- 什么 新来的那个孩子?
I've got Morse in the other room.
What, the new boy?
他看起来人挺好的 特别懂礼貌
He seemed very nice, I thought.
Very polite.
Shy, though.
就是有点害羞
你拿的什么 白兰地?
What's that, brandy?
I hope you're not leading him
astray.
你可别把人孩子带歪了
He's been in the wars.
Lost a bit of blood.
他跟人搏斗来着 失了点血
You got any stew and dumplings
you can warm through?
- 家里还有没有能热着吃的炖肉饺子什么的?
- 我去准备
I'll put something on.
你该拿黑啤 别拿白兰地
It's stout you need, not brandy.
给他喝点含铁的 能恢复他的气力
Something with a bit of iron in it.
Build his strength up.
There's a bottle at the back there.
那后面有一瓶
There you go.
给你
- Ronnie?
- 银行的Ronnie Gidderton?
Ronnie?
Ronnie Gidderton from the bank?
我记得你说他有点多愁善感
I thought you said he was a bit wet.
You've scared off all the decent
ones. Come in, Morse.
- 那又不是我的错 是你把好男人都吓跑了
- 进来吧 Morse
Don't stand on ceremony.
Budge up, Sam.
别这么拘束 挪一挪 Sam
- 你不该让我睡过去的 长官
You shouldn't have let me sleep,
sir.
- 可你看上去很需要睡一觉
Looked like you could do with it.
Mrs Thursday's done you some tea.
Win, dear.
- Thursday太太给你准备了晚饭
- 叫我Win就好 亲爱的
- 感觉好些了吗?
- 嗯 好多了 谢谢
You feeling better?
Oh, yeah. Much. Thanks.
What happened to you, then?
- 你怎么了?
Not at tea, Joan, thank you.
- 吃饭的时候别说这些 Joan 谢谢
- 我问问而已
- 我知道你的"而已"不只是而已
I'm only asking.
I know what you're "only".
- 我们家有条规矩
- 把工作放哪儿呢?
There's one rule in this house.
Where do we leave work?
丢在门口的衣帽架上
On the hallstand by the front door.
没错
Right.
那我们还有什么能谈的? 天气?
What can we talk about, then?
The weather?
Yeah, whether you're too big
for a spanking.
- 是啊 讨论你这年龄被打屁股是不是太老了
- 有种你试试啊
I'd like to see you try.
You wait till I'm back from the
army. Word of advice, Morse.
- 等我参军回来走着瞧
- 忠告 Morse
可千万别养孩子 绝对让你未老先衰
Don't have children. They'll make
you old before your time.
Frazil小姐找你 爸
A Miss Frazil on the blower, Pop.
After you called, I spoke to my old
editor, Sid Mears. He sent these.
上次你来过之后 我和之前的编辑
Sid Mears谈了下 他给我寄来了这些
He knew the Miller case?
他知道Miller案?
可能吧 他说他记得43年底
好像有个类似的事件
Perhaps. He remembered something
similar around the end of '43.
他一直惦记着这事
It'd stuck in his head.
Only, the family name was Gull.
只不过那人姓Gull
他们在Wolvercote经营一家公路旅馆
They ran a coaching inn by
Wolvercote.
I say "they". It was just
Mason Gull and his mother.
虽然说是"他们"
但只有Mason Gull和他母亲两人
但问题是 那里有个美国将军的驻地
Thing is, there was an American
general billeted there.
那时候临近诺曼底登陆 可别忘了这点
This was the build up to D-Day,
don't forget.
还有 据大家说
Anyway, this general
had taken a bit of a shine
to Mrs Gull, by all accounts,
这将军有点喜欢上Gull夫人了
and that's what led to it.
所以才造成了这局面
Sid和他的摄像师是最早赶到旅馆的一批人???
Sid and his photographer were
amongst the first out to the inn,
and got those few snaps
在军警蜂拥而至将他们赶出去之前
抓拍了这些照片
before the military police descended
on the place and turfed them out.
后来 陆军部传来消息
In the end, word came down
from the War Office -
at the very highest level -
that the story was to be spiked.
保密级别最高的那种 说这报道到此为止
诺曼底登陆迫在眉睫
我想"乱说话会有生命危险"吧
D-Day looming. "Dangerous talk
costs lives", I suppose.
如果他姓Gull 为什么Cronyn医生叫他Keith Miller?
If his name was Gull, why would
Doctor Cronyn know him as Keith
Miller?
Maybe they changed his name,
也许他们改了他的名字
buried him away in the country
somewhere, and forgot about him.
把他关在什么深山老林 结果忘了
In any event, Sid never
came across a word
不管怎样吧 Sid再没听说过有后续
没有收监也没有审判
on any subsequent committal
or trial.
The boy just disappeared.
这男孩就这么消失了
- 我不会让你失望的
- 你从未让我失望过
I won't let you down.
You never have.
准备好了吗?
Ready?
He played a record. Tosca.
Tosca?
Phillip Madison 他放了一张唱片, 歌剧托斯卡
- 托斯卡?
It's a penny dreadful of a plot.
情节相当可怕
Filled with murder, torture,
suicide.
充斥着谋杀 折磨 自杀
- 那刚好是他最拿手的
- 到高潮部分 女主角Floria Tosca
Right up his street, then. At the
climax, the heroine, Floria Tosca,
hurls herself from the battlements
of the Castel Sant'Angelo.
从圣安杰洛城堡的城垛上一跃而下
总而言之 除了他要我们知道的这第五位
In summation, then, apart from
method by which he means to dispose
of this fifth and final victim,
也是最后一位被害人的死亡方式外
我们既不知道地点 也不知道时间
更不知道被害人是谁
we know neither the where,
the when, nor the whom of it.
If the killer's sticking to
Morse's EGBDF pattern, sir,
如果凶手真的按照Morse说的
EGBDF模式杀人的话 长官
肯定是名字以F开头的某个人
it's got to be someone whose name
begins with an F.
It's Cronyn.
- 是Cronyn
What is?
- 是什么?
凶手 凶手是Cronyn
The murderer. It's Cronyn.
I appreciate your work on this,
but I think you'll find...
我很感激你的努力 但你会发现...
Cronyn approached us,
didn't he, sir? Yes, but...
- Cronyn主动接近我们的 是不是 长官?
- 是的 但...
He's the one had us running around
looking for this Keith Miller.
是他让我们绕来绕去寻找Keith Miller的
- 可Morse!
- 这是个笑话 长官 一个盲点
But Morse!
It's a joke, sir. A blind.
Keith Miller从来就不存在 长官
Keith Miller doesn't exist, sir.
把他名字的字母重新排列就得到...
Rearrange the letters of his name
and you get...
"I'm the killer."
"我是凶手"
从一开始 他就一直在耍我们...
He's been toying with us,
right from the beginning...
伪装成Cronyn医生
posing as Dr Cronyn.
So who is he really?
那他到底是谁?
Mason Gull, sir.
Mason Gull 长官
Good grief.
老天呐
Then whose body did we find
in Cronyn's consulting rooms?
那我们在Cronyn诊察室里
发现的尸体是谁?
Are you sure this is it?
Outside of the rooms in town,
- 你确定是这?
- 除了城里的那间房
这是Daniel Cronyn选民登记册上
it's the only other address
for a Daniel Cronyn
showing on the Electoral Register.
唯一的其他地址
He's been here.
Of course he has.
- 他来过这
- 他当然来过
This has been his bolt hole.
这曾是他的避难所
我想这才是Cronyn医生
Doctor Cronyn, I presume.
The real Daniel Cronyn.
真正的Daniel Cronyn
He's kept him drugged on morphine.
他一直给他打吗啡
Far enough out so that nobody
could hear his screams.
离人烟够远 这样别人就听不到他的尖叫
为什么不马上杀了他?
Why not just kill him straightaway?
Because the body at the consulting
rooms had to be fresh.
因为诊察室里的尸体
一定得是个活人
调查Gull太太谋杀的
The murder of Mrs Gull was
investigated
是牛津郡警局的Foxley督察
by Detective Inspector Foxley
of Oxford City Police.
起诉时有两位目击者到场
Two witnesses appeared for
the prosecution -
屠夫Benjamin Nimmo
slaughterman Benjamin Nimmo,
who had dropped by the inn
for a pint of ale
他当时刚好路过旅馆想喝杯酒
and found the body of Mrs Gull,
发现了Gull太太的尸体
and barmaid Gertrude Tate,
还有酒吧女招待Gertrude Tate
她当时和她8岁的女儿Evelyn在一起
who was there with her
eight-year-old daughter Evelyn.
What's the odds Mr Balfour
will confirm
你们觉得Balfour先生跟我们确认
his wife's maiden name was Tate?
他太太的娘家姓是Tate的几率有多大?
The case was heard
by His Honour Mr Justice Madison.
审理该案的法官大人是Justice Madison先生
Gull是在杀害跟这起判案有关的人
Gull's been killing anyone
connected with the trial.
He's going after Faye Madison.
他要杀Faye Madison
Now. F for Faye.
你们看 F代表Faye
她是第五名受害人
She's the fifth victim.
我们得赶紧派警员去Alfredus学院
We need to get officers
to Alfredus College at once.
难怪Gull要在电话里给我听托斯卡
That's why Gull played me Tosca
over the telephone.
Alfredus学院是牛津学者合唱协会的所在地
Alfredus College is home to
The Oxford Scholars Choral
Association.
The choir that I sing with.
So where does Tosca come in?
- 我参加过那个合唱团
- 那跟托斯卡有什么关系?
The Oxford Scholars Choral Association
我们有时候用首字母缩略来叫它
The Oxford Scholars Choral
Association.
We sometimes refer to it by acronym.
TOSCA
TOSCA.
警察打电话找你 小姐
It's the police on the telephone
for you, miss.
They said it's urgent.
The police?
- 他们说急事
- 警察?
Hello.
你好
- 就这?
- 增援马上就到
This it?
Reserves are on their way.
Think he'll come? He must know
we'll be waiting for him.
你觉得他会来?
他肯定知道我们在等他
- 他是知道
- 那你怎么知道他会来?
Oh, he knows all right.
Then how can you be sure?
This is his grand finale.
这可是他的终场高潮
怎么可能错过
He's not going to miss this.
这边 长官
Here, sir.
Gull's got her. If he's sticking
to the opera's plot,
Gull已经抓了她 如果他按照歌剧情节走
他会把她从屋顶上扔下去
he'll throw her from the roof.
There's a stair at each corner
of the quad.
门卫说这四方院每个角都有楼梯
I'll wait for the reserve to arrive.
He won't get away.
我去等增援 他跑不了的
Jesus!
老天!
我找到她了!
I've found her!
- 警长 跟我来
- 是 长官
Sergeant, follow me.
Yes, sir.
好了
OK.
Don't worry, Miss Madison.
You're safe now.
别担心 Madison小姐 你现在安全了
- Cronyn在哪?
- 他叫我别害怕 然后就走了
Where's Cronyn? He told me not
to worry and went off.
You got her. She all right?
No harm.
- 你找到她了 她没事吧?
- 没受伤
Where's Inspector Thursday?
Thursday督察呢?
Scarpia.
Scarpia
(歌剧托斯卡中的人物 警察局长)
- Morse?
- 噢...
Morse?
Oh...
Miss Madison isn't the final victim.
Madison小姐不是最后的被害者
This isn't Cronyn's plan.
I've made a mistake.
这不是Cronyn的计划 我犯了个错误
F for Faye, though.
可F是代表Faye啊
不对 不是Faye
No, it's not Faye.
It's Fred. Fred Thursday.
是Fred 是Fred Thursday
Well. Here's a how d'you do.
嗯 终于见面了
- 她在哪?
- 很安全
Where is she?
Oh, quite safe.
The proverbial sprat.
她是众所周知的诱饵
而你们就笨到上钩了
And you the mackerel.
否则你以为我怎么能把你弄到这来?
How else do you imagine
I got you up here?
When it comes to a damsel
in distress,
每当出现受困少女的情况
你们这些警察的行为总是很好预测
the boys in blue can always be
relied upon to act predictably.
我以为跳楼的是Tosca?
I thought it was Tosca
goes off the roof?
In Act Three, yes. But it's Act Two
I've always had in mind.
在第三幕的时候 是的
但我心里设计的是第二幕
The death of Scarpia -
Scarpia之死
贪腐的警察局长 死于Tosca之手
the corrupt and venal Chief of
Police - at Tosca's hand.
I'm afraid the parts are
already cast.
恐怕这一幕的演员已经订好了???
I've nothing against you personally.
我没有针对你个人的意思
You simply stand in place
of the detective inspector
whose lies put me away.
你只不过正好占着那个
用谎言将我关起来的督察的位置
Foxley
Foxley.
今天本来该是他站这陪我的
It should've been him up here
with me today.
But he died while I was... away.
可他在我不在的时候...死了
那你还等什么?
Well, what are you waiting for?
An audience. What else?
观众啊 还能等什么?
Where does Morse fit into all this?
Morse跟这一切有什么关系?
Got to be about more than torment.
不止是为了折磨吧
在图书馆的时候你本可以杀了他
为什么没下手?
You could've killed him at the
Bodleian. Why didn't you?
贝多芬有他的辛德勒 海顿有他的格里辛格
Beethoven had his Schindler.
Haydn his Griesinger.
Every great artist needs
a biographer.
每个伟大的艺术家都需要一个传记作家
Someone to bear witness
to his greatness
需要有人来证明他的伟大
and set it down for posterity.
让他流芳百世
成为我最大的成就...
How does it feel...
有什么感觉?
to be my crowning achievement?
Five's a good number,
don't you think?
5是个好数字 你不觉得吗?
又好又简单 一只手就数完
Nice and simple.
Count 'em on one hand.
You're going to keep this up,
I wouldn't mind a draw on my pipe,
你要是打算一直这么说下去的话
if it's all the same.
我不介意点下烟斗的
In lieu of a hearty breakfast.
By all means.
当然 就当是一顿丰盛的早餐吧
Oh, I've looked into the eyes of
far worse than you.
噢 我曾见过比你更凶恶的双眼
真正犯下滔天暴行的人
People who've committed real
atrocities.
And they were sane.
而且他们都神智正常
Next to them, you're nothing more
than a third-rate freak show.
跟他们相比 你不过是个三流的跳梁小丑
如同戴着假胡子的女人
胶水都顺着脸颊流下来了
A bearded lady
with glue running down her chin.
你是刺激不到我的 Thursday
You won't goad me into recklessness,
Thursday.
I'm serene.
我现在很平静
And I'll be remembered.
- 我将会被世人铭记
- 一两年吧 最多五年
A year or two. Maybe five.
放在罪犯年鉴里 你撑死就是个补充说明
Comes to the annals of crime,
you're nothing more than a footnote.
这你就错了
That's where you're wrong.
十年 也许用不了十年
他们就会证明我病愈了
Ten years - less, maybe -
they'll certify me cured.
- 我骗过他们一次 还能再骗一次
I fooled them once.
I can do it again.
- 来的正好 Morse 来的正好
Timely, Morse. Timely.
小心脚下 这地方挺滑
Watch your footing.
It's a bit slippy.
Spoletta来了 不出所料
(Scarpia的助手)
Here comes Spoletta. Right on cue.
La commedia e finita!
喜剧结束了!
Scarpia dies. You arrest me.
Scarpia死了 你逮捕我
- 这就是结局
- 我改写的话这就不是结局
That's how this ends.
Not if I rewrite it.
那你得速度点!
Then you'd better be quick!
- 都控制住了吗 Thursday?
- 算是吧 长官
All under control, Thursday?
More or less, sir, yes.
搭把手 Strange
Lend a hand, Strange.
You think it's the end?
This is where it starts.
你以为这就完了? 这是开始
That's enough out of you.
We're the same, you and me.
- 你够了
- 我俩是一样的 你和我
We bear the same burden.
Intelligence.
我们背负着同样的重担 智慧
聪明人都是孤独的 永远孤独
To be clever is to be alone.
Forever.
我在你身上看到了孤独
I see it in you.
我知道你没能拯救的是谁 Morse
I know who you couldn't save, Morse.
噢 真烦
Oh, bugger.
I broke my pipe.
我把烟斗摔坏了
Oh, bad luck.
噢 真倒霉
A spare, thankfully.
幸好只是备用的
说真的 要是刚才Morse没出现的话...
Mind you, if Morse hadn't
shown up...
Yes, well...
是的 这个...
I imagine getting back to general
duties after all this
我觉得在经历这一切之后再回去值班
will seem like a holiday. Hm?
就有点像放大假了吧?
Sir.
是 长官
Carry on.
好好干
I'll book him in.
我会将他收监
你怎么做到的?
How do you do it?
把工作丢在门口
Leave it at the front door.
因为我必须这么做
Cos I have to.
Case like this'll tear the heart
right out of a man.
像这样的案子会让人难过得喘不过气
去找些值得你守护的东西
Find something worth defending.
I thought I had...
我本以为我已经...
found something.
找到了
音乐?
Music?
我觉得音乐是个好东西
I suppose music is as good
as anything.
Go home, put your best record on...
回家 把你最喜欢的唱片放上
loud as it'll play...
声音开到最大
每一个音符都在提醒你
and with every note,
you remember...
that's something that the
darkness couldn't take from you.
总有些东西 黑暗无法从你手中夺去
Subtitles by MemoryOnSmells
http://UKsubtitles.ru.